<!-- vim: set ft=xml : -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title>Both of One Mind</title>
      <author>Charles E. Pearce</author>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Transcribed by</resp>
        <name>Paul Flo Williams</name>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>The Charles Pearce Society</publisher>
      <availability>
        <p>Charles Pearce died in 1924, making his works out of copyright in the UK as of 1995.</p>
      </availability>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>First published in the Northern Warder and Bi-Weekly Courier and Argus [Dundee Courier], Friday 31 December 1875, p.7</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en-GB">
<body>
<head type="main">Both of One Mind</head>
<head type="sub">A Christmas Story</head>
<p>The London train which stopped at Rodwell, a little
out-of-the-way station, some twenty miles from town,
was half an hour late. There had been a heavy fall
of snow the previous night, the train was a long one,
and as the engine drew up at the platform it groaned
and snorted as if complaining at the hard task it had
to perform.</p>

<p>Only one passenger alighted. A young man, fresh
coloured and fair, bright eyes and well cut, decisive
features. He was evidently well known at the sta-
tion, for the porter touched his cap when he got out
of the carriage, and the stationmaster saluted him
respectfully.</p>

<p><said>The carriage is here of course, Jones,</said> said he.</p>

<p><said>Yes, sir;</said> and the porter, expectant of future
sixpences, hastened to deposit a small leather bag in
a brougham that was waiting outside.</p>

<p><said>Good morning, John,</said> said the traveller, in a
clear, pleasant voice to the coachman, an old man,
with a face like a withered apple.</p>

<p><said>Mornin', Master Robert. A little latish this
mornin', sir.</said></p>

<p><said>Yes; but you must make up for it. It wants
half an hour of four yet.</said></p>

<p><said>Oh, we can do it Master Robert. We can do it,</said>
chuckled the old man. <said>But Mr Jonathan do like
his dinner punctual--that he do. And so he ought,
with such a appetite as he's got.</said></p>

<p><said>Then mind you don't spoil it,</said> said the young
man laughingly, as he stepped into the carriage.</p>

<p>Old John settled his hat with a knowing cock,
whipped up his horses with the precise degree of force
necessary to inform them that he would have no non-
sense, and away went the carriage over the hard snow
at the rate of ten miles an hour.</p>

<p>Robert Hanford was considered by his friends a
very fortunate young man. He was three-and-twenty,
had a splendid constitution, not a care in the world,
and above all (in his friends' estimation his best qua-
lification) was a nephew and sole relative of old Jona-
than Barton, a retired merchant in the Turkey and
Levant trade.</p>

<p>Owing to the liberal allowance made him by his
uncle, he had never had occasion to trouble his head
about a profession. But he did not allow himself to
be idle on this account, and having a decided inclina-
tion towards art, he had, by dint of hard work,
already become a very respectable painter, although
not quite the genius his admirers would have made
him out to be.</p>

<p>The only person who thought little of his produc-
tions was his uncle, who all his life had never had a
thought beyond commerce. Jonathan Barton had
married young, but his wife died a year after the mar-
riage, and since then he had taken no interest in any-
thing but his business. During ten years he had spent
abroad, he had made sufficient money to commence in
London on his own account. Fortune had favoured
him, and after thirty years close application he had
retired with a fortune which, so it was whispered on
'Change, could not be much less than a million. On
retiring he had bought an estate at Rodwell, where
he intended to spend the last years of his life.</p>

<p>He was much attached to his nephew, Robert, who
had lived with him ever since a boy of ten, and there
were very few things the latter wished for that he
was denied. But with all his indulgence the old man
had a decided will of his own, and if he made up his
mind to anything, it was no easy matter to turn him.
The only point upon which he had ever seriously quar-
relled with his nephew was in relation to the lad's
fondness for painting, and that, as he said, he could
<emph>not</emph> understand. Had it been shooting, or hunting, or
fishing (the old man was very fond of fishing), there
would have been some sense in it, but to shut him-
self up in a pigstye (the irreverent term he applied to
the disorder of a studio so beloved by artists) and to
go on day after day trying to paint on canvass that
which was done a thousand times better by nature,
seemed to him an utter waste of time. However, in
spite of his objection, he allowed Robert to have his
own way, and after the first protest never again inter-
fered with his fancy.</p>

<p>On his side it may be fairly said that the young
man did what he could to please his uncle. He never
missed dining with him at least once a week. He
submitted cheerfully to the old man's somewhat
prosy stories, most of them relating to smart business
transactions of bygone days, he went out fishing
with him occasionally, and he even made the fourth
at a rubber at whist, in company with an old white-
headed fellow who had been head clerk of Jonathan
Barton &amp; Co. for many a long year, and the clergy-
man of the parish, whom Barton had known in
his youth, and with whom he had even since main-
tained a friendship. In addition he put up with his
frequent irritability, endured his whims, and this
not for any interested motive, but because he really
had a strong affection for his uncle.</p>

<p>It was one of these weekly visits he was paying
when he is introduced to the reader, and as by this
time he had reached Shrublands (for so the estate
was called), we may as well follow him thither.</p>

<p>The dinner was over, and uncle and nephew drew
near the fire to enjoy their wine and dessert. A strong
contrast did they present, the old man with his
withered wrinkled face, thin silvery hair, and
shrunken limbs, and the young one with his fresh
open looks, cheery laugh, and well knit, if slight,
frame. And yet there was a likeness between them,
for each had the same resolute mouth and chin, and
at times there was a striking similarity in their
voices, allowing, of course, for the difference in
age.</p>

<p>It was very cold, and Jonathan Barton was sitting
close to the fire in a massive arm chair, quaintly
carved, and the back, arms, and seat was covered
with crimson velvet, whose warm tint seemed to
bring out the pearly tint of his hair in greater
relief. He had a rug thrown over his knees, and
was sipping his port with great contentment.</p>

<p><said>Ah, when I was your age, Bob, I thought nothing
of walking five miles through the frost and snow to
business, sometimes without my breakfast too.
Nowadays you young men must have their first class
carriages and omnibuses, ay, and a cigar to boot.</said></p>

<p><said>And they are not so well off as some others I
could name,</said> returned Robert laughing. <said>There's
an idle dog I know who, thanks to an indulgent old
uncle, doesn't even have any business to go to.</said></p>

<p><said>He's not idle, Bob; no, I'll give him that due.
He's not idle, only mistaken. And that reminds me
of something I've been going to speak to you about
for a long time.</said></p>

<p><said>Indeed, and what is it?</said></p>

<p><said>Just fill my glass, lad, and I'll tell you. Thank
you. Well, it's just this. I'm seventy-two next
Christmas Eve, and though I'm pretty hale and
hearty, I cannot expect to live for ever. Now, you
know I'm very fond of you, and would like to see
you fairly started in life before I go. I've let you
have your own way in everything hitherto, and
want you to let me have my own way in this.</said></p>

<p><said>My dear uncle,</said> said Robert, leaning forward and
shaking the old man by the hand, <said>your only fault
is that you are too good to me. Of course you shall
have your own way if it's anything reasonable.</said></p>

<p><said>Reasonable, Bob,</said> said Jonathan a little sharply,
<said>why you don't think I'd ask you to do anything
unreasonable, do you?</said></p>

<p><said>Oh, certainly not,</said> observed Robert, inwardly
ejaculating that there was nothing more likely.</p>

<p><said>Very well, then. I'm sure you'll say when you
hear what I'm going to ask you that nothing in the
world could be more reasonable. The fact is, Bob, I
want you to get married.</said></p>

<p><said>Married, sir,</said> exclaimed Robert with a start.</p>

<p><said>Ah, I thought it would be a pleasant surprise for
you,</said> chuckled the old man.</p>

<p><said>But, really, uncle,</said> began Bob confusedly.</p>

<p><said>Why, you don't object, do you; confound it, sir,
you're old enough.</said></p>

<p><said>Yes, I'm old enough; but you took me rather
unawares. Curiously enough, only I didn't like to
open the matter to you, it was a subject upon which
I--I was going to speak to you myself.</said></p>

<p><said>So much the better, Bob, then we can come at
once to business. There's nothing like business, you
know. Now, the lady I've got in my eye for you is
----</said></p>

<p><said>I beg your pardon, uncle,</said> exclaimed Robert, his
cigar dropping from his hand unheeded. <said>What did
you say?</said></p>

<p><said>The lady I have in my mind's eye for you,</said> re-
peated Mr Barton, slowly, <said>is Miss Leslie, the
daughter of my old friend, Jack Leslie of Crutched
Friars.</said></p>

<p>The young man did not at once reply, but stared at
his uncle in bewilderment. <said>Surely,</said> he faltered at
last, <said>you must be joking.</said></p>

<p><said>Joking, sir? What should I joke for? No, I'm
perfectly serious, and what is more, I've written this
very morning to ask them to spend Christmas with
me. Confound it, Bob, you're a lucky dog if she only
turns out half as pretty as she bid fair to be two years
ago. She's none of your boarding school misses I can
tell you, but a sensible woman, and clever too into
the bargain.</said></p>

<p>Robert rose from his chair somewhat disturbed in
manner. <said>My dear uncle,</said> said he, <said>I would do
anything rather than this. I have never seen the
lady, in the first place. She may not like me; be-
sides, I've no particular wish to get married.</said></p>

<p><said>Why, didn't you say just now you were going to
speak to me on the subject?</said></p>

<p><said>Yes, but----</said></p>

<p><said>Very well, then, the matter's settled. I tell you
seriously, Bob, I've set my heart on this, and unless
you wish to quarrel you'll do what I ask you.</said></p>

<p><said>I do not wish to quarrel with you, uncle,</said> re-
plied the young man firmly, <said>but I cannot marry
Miss Leslie.</said></p>

<p><said>Stop, Bob,</said> cried the old man, his face flushing with
excitement, <said>don't irritate me. I mean what I say,
mind,</said> and he emphasised his words with a thump of
his stick on the ground.</p>

<p><said>And I mean what <emph>I</emph> say,</said> returned Robert, a
little nettled. <said>We may as well have it out. The
fact is I cannot marry the lady you have chosen for
me for the simple reason that I have chosen one for
myself.</said></p>

<p>At these words Mr Barton's face grew redder, the
veins in his forehead swelled, and his right hand
clutched his stick convulsively. He attempted to
speak; there was a gurgling sound in his throat, and
the next moment he fell back in his chair.</p>

<p>In great alarm Robert rushed to him and undid his
collar. Then, dashing some water in his face, he saw
to his great relief the old man open his eyes, and his
natural colour return.</p>

<p><said>Forgive me, uncle,</said> he cried.</p>

<p><said>You will do what I ask?</said></p>

<p><said>I cannot,</said> he returned, sadly, <said>without making
myself a scoundrel.</said></p>

<p><said>Then you may go to the deuce if you like.</said></p>

<p>He stretched out his left hand feebly and seized
the bellrope. Upon the bell sounding the old butler
entered the room.</p>

<p><said>Parks,</said> said Mr Barton, in a hard, dry voice,
<said>Mr Robert leaves this house to-night. Get the
carriage ready in time for the next train.</said></p>

<p>Parks stood rooted to the floor in great amazement
at this speech. He stared first at his master, who
with his face averted from his nephew was sitting
with his body bent forward and his head resting on his
hand, and then at Robert standing on the hearthrug,
his back to the fire, his face pale and determined, and
his eyes looking straight before him.</p>

<p><said>I beg your pardon, sir,</said> said he at last.</p>

<p><said>Mr Robert leaves this house to-night. I spoke
plainly enough,</said> replied Jonathan, impatiently.</p>

<p><said>It's quite right, Parks,</said> said Robert, in a low
voice. <said>You can get my things ready.</said></p>

<p>Again Parks looked from one to the other and then
withdrew, apparently completely prostrated by the
order he had received.</p>

<p><said>Good-bye, uncle,</said> said Robert, holding out his
hand.</p>

<p>Jonathan did not reply. There was, however, a
little twitching of the muscles of the mouth and a
slight movement of the right arm, but soon the lines
in his face hardened and his face was as immoveable
as before.</p>

<p>The young man waited a minute and then walked
towards the door. When he reached it he looked
back at the figure in the chair and paused irresolutely.
It was only for a few seconds. <said>No,</said> he murmured,
<said>not even for his sake.</said></p>

<p>And the next moment he was gone.</p>

<milestone unit="tb"/>

<p><said>Do you really love me as much as you say,
Robert?</said></p>

<p><said>More than I can say, darling.</said></p>

<p>And he kissed the blushing face upturned to his as
an earnest of his words.</p>

<p><said>It does seem so strange, dear. What have I done
that you should care for me?</said></p>

<p>What had she done indeed! She might as well
have asked why her eyes were soft and pleading, why
her mouth seemed intended by nature to kiss and to
be kissed, why her voice was music itself? Her
whole being was womanly and tender, and Robert
Hanford could no more help loving her than he could
help breathing. There was no arguing the question
as to why he did; it was part of his life, and to lose
her would be to lose his better self.</p>

<p><said>But what will your uncle say when he knows
you have married only a poor music teacher?</said></p>

<p><said>I cannot say. Perhaps I never shall know.</said></p>

<p><said>Why do you not mean to tell him?</said></p>

<p><said>He knows already as much as he will know from
my lips,</said> returned the young man gravely.</p>

<p><said>You are keeping something back from me that
is not right, dearest,</said> said she softly.</p>

<p>The fire burning low in the grate suddenly sent up
a flicker that lighted up the old furniture with which
the room was furnished, and made it look quite pictur-
esque. Even Daisy Ashley, beautiful as she was,
seemed more beautiful as it glanced on the harmonious
lines of her figure. She was leaning against the mantel-
shelf, one small foot resting on the fender, its
coquettish tip just peeping from beneath her dress,
and as she spoke she turned her eyes upon Robert
who was standing by her. It was a half-timid, half-
trustful look, and the young man felt as if no secret
would be safe in his breast with so lovely a confessor by
his side.</p>

<p><said>My darling,</said> said he, placing his arm around her
waist and drawing her to him, <said>I did not intend to
tell you, at least not yet awhile, but perhaps it is for
the best. You think me rich, do you not?</said></p>

<p><said>I cannot tell,</said> she said simply. <said>I have never
thought about it. To know I had your love has been
sufficient for me,</said> she added with a little blush.</p>

<p>He smoothed the wavy hair from the white fore-
head and kissed it. <said>My pet,</said> he whispered, <said>yester-
day I had no care for wealth because it was in my
grasp. To-day when I have it not I wish for it--for
your sake not for my own.</said></p>

<p><said>Why how foolish that is now,</said> she returned with
a bright smile. <said>Look at this room and tell me if
any of your rich friends would care to have it. And
yet I have been happy, very happy. If it were not
for poor papa I should never miss the riches we once
had.</said></p>

<p><said>Dare you then trust in one who had nothing but
his own right hand to battle with poverty.</said></p>

<p><said>Yes,</said> said she fearlessly, <said>but I do not <choice><corr>quite</corr><orig>quit</orig></choice>
understand. You are not so poor as that, are you?</said></p>

<p><said>Yes,</said> he returned with a little sigh. <said>I have
quarrelled with my uncle, and we have parted.</said></p>

<p><said>Quarrelled,</said> she repeated, as if to herself. Then
turning upon him her large brown eyes, as if she
would read his very soul, she drooped her head upon
his breast and gave a little sob.</p>

<p><said>You have done this for me, Robert. Your looks
tell me so. Oh, how could you? I have been very
wicked. No, you must not kiss me. You must go
to your uncle, who loves you very much, and forget
me.</said></p>

<p>But he held her tighter in his arms, and whispered
that he would not give her up for a thousand uncles.
In a few words he told her how his uncle has wanted
him to marry some one else, and how he had refused;
and at this confession her love overcame the restraint
she would have put upon it, and she nestled closer
to his side, for she felt now that he indeed cared for
her.</p>

<p><said>There, you are a very bad boy, and I shall never
forgive you,</said> said she, with a pretty shake of her
head, as she disengaged herself from his arm. <said>And
see, it is six o'clock, and papa will be home in a
quarter of an hour, and there'll be no tea ready for
him, and all through you.</said></p>

<p>And tripping lightly over the floor she busied her-
self in lighting the candles, filling the kettle, and
arranging the tea table, all of which operations, pro-
saic enough under ordinary circumstances, seemed to
Robert's fascinated eyes to be invested with a poetry
and grace he could not have believed possible.</p>

<p>And then Mr Ashley, a man evidently in weak
health, with a weary look on his brow, came in, and
the three sat down to tea, Daisy presiding in a way
that was simply bewitching.</p>

<milestone unit="tb"/>

<p>It wanted but a fortnight of Christmas, and to
Robert and Daisy, absorbed in each other and their
plans for the future, the hours flew by like minutes.
Not so was it with Jonathan Barton. Since his quar-
rel with his nephew he had become quite a changed
man. He lost his appetite, he took no interest in
anything; the <title>Times</title>, once his constant delight and
matutinal study, lay unopened on the breakfast table
every morning, and whenever he moved about it was
no longer with his former brisk step, but slowly and
dejectedly.</p>

<p><said>You ain't got much appetite this morning again,
sir,</said> said Parks, who took the dejection of his master
much to heart. <said>Why don't you have a change,
sir? Send for Master Robert, sir.</said></p>

<p><said>Parks,</said> said Jonathan, in something like his old
sharp tone, <said>Have the kindness not to mention my--
that gentleman's name again.</said></p>

<p><said>Very good, sir, only you did seem that low----</said></p>

<p><said>How dare you say I'm low?</said> shouted the old man
irritably; <said>Hold your tongue.</said></p>

<p>And Parks shuffled out of the room in some trepi-
dation, although, as he said, when he reached the
kitchen, the master talked more like old times than
he had done since Master Robert left.</p>

<p><said>And to-morrow's my birthday,</said> muttered Jona-
than, when he was left to himself. <said>Augh, a pretty
fellow I am to have a birthday. Just tottering into
the grave. What am I to do with myself? For
thirteen years Bob--no I won't call him Bob--the
ungrateful dog, has dined with me and now of course
he won't be here. It's his own fault. Obstinacy
is the curse of all young men. I've half a mind
to go to town and dine at the club. I can't stay
here. I begin to hate the place. Yes, I <emph>will</emph> dine at
the club, and then perhaps I shall <choice><corr>hear</corr><orig>here</orig></choice> something of
Leslie. How odd my letter should come back. I
suppose he has been a fool like myself, given up
business. Well, well, there's no fool like an old fool
they say. I wonder what that rascal--no I won't
think about him any longer.</said></p>

<p>Thus muttering to himself the old man sunk back
in his chair and watched through his half-closed eyes
the flames darting up the broad chimney. He felt
very desolate and would in his heart have given all he
possessed to have seen his nephew sitting once more in
his old seat on the other side.</p>

<p>He carried out his intention of dining in town on
his birthday. Accompanied by Parks and well wrapt
up in rugs, for it was bitterly cold, he reached the
terminus safely. As he was being led across the plat-
form he stumbled, for his legs were stiff and numbed,
and he would have fallen in spite of Park's arm had
not a stranger come to his assistance.</p>

<p><said>Thank you--Why, bless my soul is it you Jack?</said></p>

<p>And the next minute the two were shaking hands
warmly.</p>

<p><said>But, deuce take it, Jack, what have you been
doing to yourself? Why, you look about as old as I
do, and there's ten years I know between us.</said></p>

<p><said>You haven't heard, I suppose,</said> began the other
hesitatingly.</p>

<p><said>Haven't heard, of course I haven't. I wrote to
you at Crutched Friars, but my letter came back.
Nothing's gone wrong, I hope?</said></p>

<p><said>Everything, my old friend; I'm a ruined man. All
is gone.</said></p>

<p><said>No,</said> said Jonathan kindly; <said>poor fellow. But
why didn't you write to me? I'm so out of the world
now, I hear nothing.</said></p>

<p><said>I could not; I couldn't face my old friends; and
if I had seen you in the street I think I should have
avoided you.</said></p>

<p><said>No, no, you wouldn't Jack. But there, come
and dine with me, and tell me all about it.</said></p>

<p><said>Well, I should like to for the sake of old times,
but I promised my daughter I would be home early.
You see <choice><corr>it's</corr><orig>its</orig></choice> Christmas Eve, and----</said></p>

<p><said>My birthday,</said> interrupted Jonathan, <said>and I'm
determined to keep it somewhere. My neph--</said> but
here his voice became a little shaky, and he turned
what he was going to say into a cough.</p>

<p><said>If you don't mind coming to my poor place,</said> said
Mr Leslie hesitatingly.</p>

<p><said>Mind coming; I should think not indeed. And
with your pretty daughter to welcome me, too. Ah,
Jack, I once had a hope that--but there, that's all
over.</said></p>

<p>Meanwhile, Parks had called a cab, and the two
friends getting inside were soon proceeding rapidly
in the direction of Islington, where Mr Leslie re-
sided.</p>

<p><said>Daisy, my dear, here is an old friend come to
see us. You remember Mr Barton, do you not?</said></p>

<p>The girl came forward to greet him, but singular
enough he scarcely noticed her proffered hand. His
gaze was directed fixedly on a young man who had
been sitting by Daisy's side, and who had risen on his
entry.</p>

<p><said>Are my old eyes deceiving me? Is it--is it really
you, Bob?</said> faltered the old man, involuntarily stretch-
ing out his hand.</p>

<p>There could be little doubt of it, for the next
moment his fingers were enclosed in a warm grasp,
and a well-known voice exclaimed--</p>

<p><said>You will forgive me now, uncle. Here is my
best excuse,</said> and he drew Daisy forward to him as
he spoke.</p>

<p>Jonathan put his hand to his head in a bewildered
fashion, and looked from one to the other.</p>

<p><said>I cannot understand it,</said> he murmured, <said>is not
this Daisy Leslie?</said></p>

<p><said>No, no,</said> replied Robert, thinking for a moment
his uncle's brain was turned, and that he really
fancied the lady he wanted him to marry was stand-
ing before him, <said>Daisy Ashley, you mean?</said></p>

<p><said>It is both,</said> said Daisy, with an appealing glance
to her father. <said>Forgive me, Robert it is the only
secret I ever kept from you, and you must have
known <emph>that</emph> some day,</said> she added, with a pretty
blush.</p>

<p>It was not Robert's turn to be puzzled, but a few
words from Mr Leslie soon explained the mystery.
After his bankruptcy his pride would not allow him
to retain his name, and so he had altered it to avoid
any recognition from those he had known in former
days.</p>

<p><said>Now that I have obeyed you, uncle,</said> said Robert
<choice><reg>slyly</reg><orig>slily</orig></choice>, <said>you will forgive me, won't you?</said></p>

<p><said>Forgive you, you dog, I've a good mind to order
you to be married to-morrow, only I don't want to
punish my little Daisy by inflicting some obstinate a
fellow upon her.</said></p>

<p><said>I think I know some one else who is obstinate,</said>
observed Robert.</p>

<p><said>Well, you both have your own way now,</said> said
Daisy laughingly, <said>so be satisfied.</said></p>

<p>And need I say that they were?</p>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>
