<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title>Old Prebble's Money</title>
      <author>Charles E. Pearce</author>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Transcribed by</resp>
        <name>Paul Flo Williams</name>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>The Charles Pearce Society</publisher>
      <availability>
        <p>Charles Pearce died in 1924, making his works out of copyright in the UK as of 1995.</p>
      </availability>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>First published in The Motherwell Times, Friday 25 December 1908</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en-GB">
<body>
<head type="main">Old Prebble's Money</head>

<p>The two men had certainly been having
high words. Jack Lanbury's lips were
white. A blaze of fury was in his dark eyes.
The emotions of <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Gregory Grigsby were
not so much in evidence. There was not the
ghost of an expression in his broad, pallid,
flabby face, not a scintillation of feeling in
his fishy orbs.</p>
<p><said>Well, young man, you have selected your
own path, and I presume you intend to pur-
sue it. I have warned you over and over
again, and now that the period of your pro-
bation is nearing its termination I wash my
hands of you.</said></p>
<p><said>They need it,</said> rejoined Jack Lanbury,
sarcastically.</p>
<p><said>No, sir, they do not,</said> retorted <abbr>Mr.</abbr>
Grigsby, raising his voice. <said>They are not
soiled by extravagance, by dissolute living,
by dissipation, by improvidence. I have, I
hope, always done my duty, and that, how-
ever unpleasant that duty may be, I've never
shirked it. I don't think, John Lanbury,
you have any reason to complain of any
shortcomings on that score.</said></p>
<p>Lanbury's reply was a shrug of the shoul-
ders.</p>
<p><said>Had you been only ordinarily prudent
nothing would have given me greater plea-
sure than to further your interests with
Catherine Vernon, but I had to do my duty
to my dear friend, to her, and to yourself
----</said></p>
<p><said>I wish you'd leave me out of your duty,
<abbr>Mr.</abbr> Grigsby,</said> jerked in Jack, angrily.</p>
<p><said>No, sir, I will not. I am not to be turned
either to the right or the left. The justifica-
tion of the course I have been compelled to
pursue is around you--at this very moment.</said></p>
<p><abbr>Mr.</abbr> Grigsby accompanied his solemn ad-
juration with a wave of his fat hand.</p>
<p>The room was unmistakably luxurious.
Everything showed the owner to be a man of
taste. The general air of litter and the sus-
picion of tobacco smoke indicated bachelor-
dom, to say nothing of the tantalus, the
syphons, the cigar box on a side table and
the stack of pipes on the wall by the side of
the fireplace. The most noticeable article in
the room was perhaps the overmantel. It
was profusely decorated with folded papers,
mostly of an ominous blue colour, stuck be-
hind the frame, in between the china, thrown
carelessly in the divisions devoted to miscel-
laneous articles.</p>
<p><said>Is it worth while pursuing this conversa-
tion any longer, <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Grigsby? It's not very
entertaining,</said> rejoined Jack.</p>
<p><said>I quite agree with you, sir--nor instruc-
tive.</said></p>
<p><said>Don't say that--surely everything you
say must be instructive--though perhaps
--you won't mind my pointing out--a trifle
dull.</said></p>
<p><said>To the frivolous-minded and the light-
headed no doubt it is. We will waive that
point. Before I leave I want to have a de-
finite answer to the question I put to you a
few minutes ago when you very rudely told
me to mind my own business. As your trus-
tee and as Miss Vernon's trustee it is my
business to ask you whether you, in pursu-
ance of the terms of my dear friend Prebble's
bequest, intend to ask Catherine Vernon to
be your wife?</said></p>
<p>The answer came like the pellet from a
popgun.</p>
<p><said>No.</said></p>
<p><said>Very good. Miss Vernon is to be con-
gratulated on your decision.</said></p>
<p><abbr>Mr.</abbr> Grigsby rose to go, when his eye
settled on a violin case lying on a settee.</p>
<p><said>Is that your last piece of folly?</said> said he,
pointing a stubby forefinger at the case.</p>
<p><said>Yes.</said></p>
<p><said>I'm told you gave £600 for the instru-
ment.</said></p>
<p><said>Yes.</said></p>
<p><said>A wicked, wicked waste,</said> almost groaned
<abbr>Mr.</abbr> Grigsby. <said>To think that my hard-
earned money should be squandered on
fiddles!</said></p>
<p>Jack Lanbury did not reply. He rang the
bell instead.</p>
<p><said>Show <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Grigsby to the door, Simmons.</said></p>
<p>It was a polite intimation to get out. A
venomous light flashed in <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Grigsby's
eyes.</p>
<p><said>You may like to know, sir,</said> said he,
<said>that I'm going straight to my lawyer.</said></p>
<p><said>You may go--anywhere you like.</said></p>
<p><said>The slimy old rascal. I'll wager that
within twenty-four hours I shall have a writ
for that £100 I owe him,</said> exclaimed Jack
Lanbury. <said>Anyhow, it'll be the <foreign xml:lang="fr" rend="r">chef
d'œuvre</foreign> of my collection,</said> he added, with a
reckless laugh.</p>
<p>He went to the violin case and took out
the instrument gently and lovingly.</p>
<p>Jack Lanbury was an accomplished ama-
teur, and he could not resist buying the
Strad, though the £600 he paid for it would
have gone a long way towards paying off his
pressing liabilities.</p>
<p>He swept the bow across the strings. The
rich full resonant tones of the lower notes,
the sweetness of the high ones, set his nerves
vibrating with exquisite pleasure. He soon
became absorbed, and did not hear the
entrance of Simmons.</p>
<p><said>A gentleman, sir, to see you.</said></p>
<p>Simmons handed his master a card.
<q>Christopher Stocks,</q> was the name it bore.
Jack Lanbury did not know <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Stocks, but
he would see him.</p>
<p>A little old gentleman with a yellow, dried
up complexion and wearing an obvious wig,
came excitedly into the room and almost ran
to Jack, who was still holding the violin.</p>
<p><said>Ah,</said> cried the visitor, <said>I heard you
playing, and I said no violin but a Strad
could produce such a tone. But you will per-
mit me to examine it to make sure.</said></p>
<p><said>To make sure of what?</said> asked Jack,
rather taken aback by this unceremonious
proceeding.</p>
<p><said>That it is a Strad, of course,</said> answered
<abbr>Mr.</abbr> Stocks, sharply. <said>I am a collector, and
already possess one Strad, a <choice><corr>Guarnerius</corr><orig>Guarnarius</orig></choice>, a
Stainer, and two Amatis, but my Strad is
not so perfect as this.</said></p>
<p>The <choice><corr>camaraderie</corr><orig>cameraderie</orig></choice> of the musician was
aroused. Jack handed the violin to the visi-
tor, who went over its points with feverish
anxiety.</p>
<p><said>Perfect--perfect,</said> he muttered. <said>I must
have it. <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Lanbury, I will give you
£1,000.</said></p>
<p><said>But it's not for sale.</said></p>
<p><said>Aha, you know its value and you are a
man of business. Quite right. Come--
£1,100.</said></p>
<p><said>No. I repeat I'm not going to sell it.</said></p>
<p><said>Because I have not offered you enough.
Name your own price, <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Lanbury, and I'll
meet you if possible.</said></p>
<p><said>It's no good. I tell you I've fallen in
love with the violin and I'm going to keep it.
As a violinist you ought to understand what
I feel.</said></p>
<p><said>Ah, but I'm not a violinist. I'm a col-
lector. I cannot play a note.</said></p>
<p><said>And you would keep the poor thing in a
glass case and condemn it to dumbness,</said>
cried Jack, indignantly. <said>No, a thousand
times no.</said></p>
<p><abbr>Mr.</abbr> Stocks gasped for breath. He ceased
to pester, however, any more.</p>
<p><said>Very well, <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Lanbury. If you change
your mind you must give me the refusal. I
am disappointed--but since you are deter-
mined--well, good day, sir.</said></p>
<p>And <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Stocks departed as dejected as be-
fore he was excited.</p>
<p>Jack Lanbury soon forgot <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Christopher
<cb n="2"/>
Stocks. It seemed to him as though he had
never played upon a violin before, so im-
measurably superior was the Strad to any
other of which he had had experience. At
the end of an hour he laid by the instrument
with a sigh. He had to descend from the
clouds and think over his earthly affairs.</p>
<p>Without a doubt he had been very foolish,
but the artistic temperament must have its
fling. Certainly he had enjoyed life since he
was twenty-one, and did not regret flinging
away £5,000 in four years and getting into
debt to the tone of £1,000 more, but for one
thing. It had made marriage to Kitty Ver-
non impossible.</p>
<p>But for his extravagance he might have
carried out the absurd injunction laid down
in the will of <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Grigsby's <soCalled>dear friend</soCalled>
Prebble. He wasn't quite sure, however, for
that injunction imposed a restriction on his
independence which he resented.</p>
<p>The will was certainly very ridiculous.
Prebble was an old bachelor, and a lifelong
friend of the fathers of Jack Lanbury and
Kitty Vernon. They had started in busi-
ness about the same time, Prebble soon dis-
tancing the other two in the race for wealth.
James Lanbury and Henry Vernon married
and spent all they earned, and died poor.</p>
<p>The conditions were: First that Jack was
to have £5,000 on his reaching his 21st year,
Kitty receiving a modest allowance of £150
a year. Second, if by the time Jack was
twenty-five he had proposed to Kitty and
they were married, they were to divide the
residue between them. Third, if Kitty re-
fused to marry Jack, the residue was to go
to the young man. Fourth, if on the other
hand he did not propose, then the young
woman would take the whole of the fortune.</p>
<p>Of this utterly unreasonable will <abbr>Mr.</abbr>
Gregory Grigsby was the sole executor, and
of old Prebble's money the sole trustee.</p>
<p>The position when Jack was within a fort-
night of reaching his twenty-fifth year, with
Kitty still unproposed to, is best expressed
in Jack Lanbury's own words.</p>
<p><said>My only objection to Kitty Vernon is
that she is herself. If she were anybody else
I think I should fall in love with her. Old
Prebble's will I suspect is the obstacle. She
irritates me and I irritate her. Marriage
would mean a cat and dog life. We gene-
rally snarl at each other, and if I asked her
to marry me she'd suspect my motive--
money. On the other hand I can't risk a re-
fusal--that would lose her every farthing,
and I'm not going to be mean and despicable
enough to ask her hoping she'll say no. I'd
rather hold my tongue and let the fortune go
to her.</said></p>
<p>But another reason prevented him from
proposing to Kitty. There was a man in the
case. He had seen her with the Honourable
Sidney Carnforth, and in his judgment (or
jealousy) he decided that the Honourable
Sidney's attentions were acceptable to the
young lady.</p>
<p>It was very galling. Everything had gone
so as to place him in the worst possible
light to Kitty.</p>
<p><said>I know I'm a silly fool,</said> he muttered, bit-
ing his lips. <said>I know I'm a spendthrift. I
know I've been going the pace that kills. But
why on earth should old Grigsby din it into
Kitty's ears?</said></p>
<p>Ten days went over. In four days more the
time appointed by the eccentric Prebble
would expire. Jack Lanbury would then be
twenty-five.</p>
<p>During those ten days the situation had
not changed. The outlook was as black as
ever. The collection round the overmantel
had increased, and nothing but bankruptcy
could extricate him from his web of difficul-
ties.</p>
<p>For one small mercy he had reason to be
grateful. Grigsby had not issued a writ, as
he expected, to recover his £100. Indeed,
Grigsby had not troubled him in any way.</p>
<p>And the violin? Well, he had devoted him-
self to it incessantly, but it had not dis-
placed Kitty. In its sweetest tones he heard
Kitty's voice, in its most pathetic passages he
saw her pleading eyes.</p>
<p>He resolved to exorcise the sorceress.</p>
<p><said>I won't endure it any longer,</said> he ex-
claimed angrily. <said>I'll write to her and for-
mally renounce my claim. It's the proper
thing to do. I ought to have thought of it be-
fore. I was a brute to keep the poor girl in
suspense. When she gets my letter she'll be
free to marry Sid Carnforth, and I shall be
easier in my mind--much easier.</said></p>
<p>He wrote a formal epistle after about a
dozen attempts, and decided he was easier.
Thrusting the letter in his pocket he went
out to post it. The afternoon was delightfully
tempting for a stroll. He went towards
Hyde-park Corner; the letter lay peacefully
in his pocket. He had forgotten all about it.</p>
<p>He entered the park and strolled on to the
Row, and did not remember the letter until
he had reached Kensington-gardens.</p>
<p>In spite of his having as he thought made
up his mind he found himself revolving the
question anew.</p>
<p><said>I'm right--I'm sure I'm right,</said> he mur-
mured. <said>Directly I come to a pillar-box I'll
--I beg your pardon!</said></p>
<p>In his abstraction he had nearly cannoned
against a lady. He lifted his hat; their eyes
met.</p>
<p><said>Kitty!</said></p>
<p><said>Jack!</said></p>
<p><said>I--I was just thinking about you,</said> he
blurted out in confusion.</p>
<p><said>Thanks. That must be a novelty.</said></p>
<p>He had no reply in readiness for this sar-
casm. He turned and kept pace with her in
silence.</p>
<p><said>I'm de trop as usual,</said> muttered Jack.
<said>I reckon she's going out to meet the other man.
I'd better clear out.</said></p>
<p><said>Kitty----</said></p>
<p><said>Well?</said> said she, without turning her
head.</p>
<p><said>I made a stupid mistake just now.</said></p>
<p><said>Is that anything new?</said></p>
<p><said>Of course not,</said> he replied hastily, his
face flushing. Kitty's tone was even more
bitter.</p>
<p><said>And your latest blunder?</said> she calmly in-
quired.</p>
<p><said>It's obvious. I was going in the opposite
direction when I met you. I'll repair my
mistake as soon as possible. Good-bye.</said></p>
<p><said>Wait a moment, Jack, I want to talk to
you. I'm not going to say anything spiteful
so you may as well listen.</said></p>
<p><said>I never thought anything you said to me
was spiteful,</said> he returned, gently.</p>
<p><said>Jack, I'm in a horrible predicament,</said> at
last Kitty broke out, in a sort of desperation.
<said>I know, of course, you can't help me per-
sonally, but I feel I must tell someone, and
as you've been as silly as myself, why at least
you'll sympathise.</said></p>
<p><said>Sympathetic, Kitty, of course. As for
your being as silly as myself--well, you
don't know what an idiot I've been. But
what's the matter, darling?</said></p>
<p><said>It's just this,</said> replied the young lady,
taking no notice of the word of endearment
which in view of the determination Jack had
come to was wholly superfluous. <said>I've been
playing a good deal at bridge lately, and I've
got frightfully into debt. I--I owe fifty
pounds.</said></p>
<p><said>And I owe twenty times as much. We're
companions in misfortune,</said> said Jack dis-
mally.</p>
<p><said>Yes, I know you've been frightfully ex-
travagant, but you haven't gambled.</said></p>
<p><said>I'm not so sure. But, Kitty, I wouldn't,
if I were you, let such a trifle as £50 worry
you. In four days time you know you'll be
entitled to £100,000.</said></p>
<p>Kitty looked solemnly straight before her.
Nothing could be gathered from her expres-
sion.</p>
<p><said>That just reminds me,</said> went on Jack, a
little nervously. <said>I have a letter in my
pocket for you. I was going to post it, but
as I've met you I--I shall save a penny,
<cb n="3"/>
which is something in these hard times,</said> he
added, with a ghastly attempt at a smile.</p>
<p>He pulled the letter out of his pocket and
handed it to her.</p>
<p><said>I'm not obliged to read it now, am I?
It'll do when I get home, won't it? Not very
important, I suppose?</said></p>
<p><said>Well--er--it is rather important. It has
to do with--with the money you're entitled
to when I'm twenty-five if----</said></p>
<p>He couldn't complete the sentence. Some-
thing stuck in his throat.</p>
<p><said>Oh--then perhaps I had better look at
it.</said></p>
<p>Jack Lanbury turned his head away. He
clenched his hands till the nails were nearly
in the flesh in the effort to control himself.</p>
<p>A minute--sixty awful seconds of suspense.</p>
<p><said>Thanks, Jack, for your letter, but it
doesn't help me out of my difficulty.</said></p>
<p>Jack looked round furtively--a little dis-
appointed maybe. Kitty did not seem very
much disturbed.</p>
<p><said>Dash it,</said> he murmured. <said>When a man
tried to be generous to a woman his gene-
rosity's never appreciated.</said></p>
<p><said>No,</said> she repeated, <said>it doesn't help me.
It's quite true that when you're twenty-five
I shall, since you've refused to marry me,
have plenty of money, but I shall have to
wait. To-day is Monday, it's four days to
Friday, your birthday, and goodness knows
how long <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Grigsby will take to hand me
my fortune. In the meantime this horrid
gambling debt is hanging round my neck. It
wouldn't matter so much if I didn't owe it
to a man to whom I won't be under an obli-
gation--I dislike him too much. You can
understand my anxiety, can't you, Jack?</said></p>
<p><said>Of course. Who is the man--but per-
haps I oughtn't to ask.</said></p>
<p><said>Yes, you may. I don't mind your know-
ing. Now that we're nothing to each other
--after your letter you know--I can take you
into my confidence. It's Sidney Carnforth.</said></p>
<p><said>The deuce it is,</said> exclaimed the startled
Jack. <said>You owe the bounder £50 and--and
you dislike him?</said></p>
<p>Kitty said nothing. She only screwed up
her lips and nodded.</p>
<p>Jack drew a long breath, and his face
flushed for a moment and then went very
pale.</p>
<p><said>Look here, Kit, you shall have the money
in two hours' time,</said> he burst out, hastily.</p>
<p><said>But, Jack dear, you haven't got it.
You're up to your neck in debts, and no one
will lend you a farthing,</said> cried Kitty.</p>
<p><said>Who told you that--Grigsby?</said></p>
<p><said>Ye--yes.</said></p>
<p><said>I thought so--and I dare say he's told you
a few other pleasant things about me. For
once both he and you--I apologise for coup-
ling his name with yours--are wrong. I've no
need to borrow. A week or so ago I refused
an offer of £1,100 for a <choice><corr>Stradivarius</corr><orig>Straduarius</orig></choice> for which
I only gave £600. I've only to take the in-
strument to the collector who wants it and I
get his cheque.</said></p>
<p><said>You mustn't sell your Strad. Why, it
would be like selling your own flesh and
blood.</said></p>
<p><said>That's nothing to do with you, Kitty.
I'd sell anything to help you and--and to
spite Sid Carnforth.</said></p>
<p>The expression of Kitty's eyes changed
once more--they were wonderful eyes for re-
flecting her varying moods. They seemed
now half distressed, half amused.</p>
<p><said>It's wrong to have a spite against any-
body, Jack. Anyhow, I'm not going to let
you part with your violin. I'm quite sorry
I told you about my scrape.</said></p>
<p>Jack in his impetuosity had hurried Kitty,
so that by this time they were in Kensing-
ton Gore. A newsvendor on his bicycle was
opposite the Albert Hall, distributing his
stock to a crowd of ragged urchins. Some
had already sped away to find customers,
bawling at the top of their voices, <said>Panic
in the City!</said></p>
<p>For a moment Jack's attention was ar-
rested. He bought a paper and opened it.</p>
<p>He uttered a cry of astonishment. This
was what he read:</p>
<p><q>Panic on the Stock Exchange. The bears
caught in a market rig. Arrest of <abbr>Mr.</abbr>
Gregory Grigsby.</q></p>
<p><said>What's the matter, Jack,</said> cried Kitty.
<said>Have you lost any money?</said></p>
<p>His face had suddenly gone white, and the
hand that held the paper trembled a little.</p>
<p><said>No--I--oh, Kitty--Kitty--Kitty--the de-
testable scoundrel!</said></p>
<p>The girl eagerly questioned him. Bit by
bit the truth came out. <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Grigsby, the
City financier, has speculated with trust
money, old Prebble's included, and had lost
every penny. Kitty's fortune had gone.</p>
<p><said>Poor Kitty--oh, I am sorry.</said></p>
<p><said>I'm not quite sure I am,</said> said she,
quietly. <said>I always hated that dreadful
money. It was like a stone wall between us.
Don't let's talk about it any more. I want
to make a confession. I haven't been play-
ing at bridge and I haven't lost any money
to Sidney Carnforth, so you needn't sell your
Strad.</said></p>
<p><said>I'm glad,</said> rejoined Jack drily. <said>But
why did you invent the thing?</said></p>
<p><said>It wasn't all invention. That part about
disliking Sidney Carnforth was quite true.</said></p>
<p>Jack's eyes brightened. But for all that
he couldn't see through Kitty's puzzle. Why
did she invent the story, he asked again.</p>
<p><said>Because <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Grigsby said that besides
being a spendthrift you were heartless, sel-
fish, and all that a man shouldn't be. I
wanted to find out a little about you; and
--and your letter and your offering to sell
your Strad told me that what I had heard
was false. I can see now why that wicked
old gentleman did not want you to marry me.
He was in difficulties and thought perhaps if
I didn't marry he could put off paying me,
whereas if you said you would marry me you
might have insisted upon going into matters,
and you'd have found out his wickedness.</said></p>
<p><said>I believe you're right, dear. Perhaps
when the old rascal's affairs are wound up
there may be something out of the wreck for
you, but in the meantime? Certainly that
<del>that</del> Strad must go.</said></p>
<p><said>Certainly it mustn't,</said> retorted Kitty,
energetically. <said>I shall take a situation.</said></p>
<p>Jack had his eyes fixed on the column con-
taining an account of the <soCalled>panic.</soCalled> Con-
siderable space was devoted to <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Grigsby's
collapse and the reasons which had led to it.
He had sold heavily various stocks which
had gone up instead of down as he expected.
The immediate cause was, however, a cer-
tain gold-mining company, the shares of
which had gone up by leaps and bounds,
especially during the past week. Three
months ago they would have been purchased
at half-a-crown, they were now near five
pounds apiece.</p>
<p><said>Great Scott,</said> suddenly shouted Jack.
<said>Hi! hansom! Jump in Kitty--quick!</said></p>
<p>Never had Jack Lanbury been so excited.
Kitty dared not ask what had happened. She
could only imagine a fresh misfortune.</p>
<p><said>Where--where are we going?</said> she asked,
hesitatingly, when they were inside the cab.</p>
<p><said>To the City. I've just discovered I've
got £10,000 I didn't know I possessed. Three
months ago an old friend who was hard up,
persuaded me to buy 2,000 shares he held in
the Great King Gold Mining Company. He
didn't mean to part with them, but he was
cornered and had no alternative. Anyhow,
I planked down £250 to oblige him and--
and, what do you think, Kit?--they're now
worth £10,000 and what's more it's the rise
in price that has downed old Grigsby. You
don't understand these things, but you'll
know a little when you see me with a cheque
for the money. We're off now to sell out
and--hurrah! I'll keep the Strad.</said></p>
<p><said>Oh, Jack--Jack, how glad I am.</said></p>
<p>He could feel her trembling slightly. His
arm went round her waist immediately. It
was only natural.</p>
<p><said>Kitty,</said> he whispered. <said>Give me back
my letter. I want to write you another--
<cb n="4"/>
and yet that would be stupid. No, you shall
hear at once what I want to say. It's the
simplest question in the world and all you've
got to do is to say yes.</said></p>
<p>Is there any necessity to quote Jack's ques-
tion or Kitty's answer?</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
