<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title>The Severed Silk Scarf</title>
      <author>Charles E. Pearce</author>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Transcribed by</resp>
        <name>Paul Flo Williams</name>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>The Charles Pearce Project</publisher>
      <availability>
        <p>Charles Pearce died in 1924, making his works out of copyright in the UK as of 1995.</p>
      </availability>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>First published in the Whitstable Times and Herne Bay Herald, <date when="1904-05-21">Saturday 21 May 1904</date></bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en-GB">
<body>
<head type="main">The Severed Silk Scarf</head>

<p>The room resounded with applause. Men and
women vied with each other in complimenting the
dexterous swordsman who, tossing a silk scarf in
the air, severed it before it reached the ground.</p>

<p><said>I fear your scarf is utterly ruined, <abbr>Mrs.</abbr>
Verne,</said> said the young soldier, picking up the two
portions and presenting them with a bow to the
lady who stood near him.</p>

<p><said>I gave you full permission, Captain Calverley,
to do what you liked with it,</said> said she.</p>

<p><said>Then,</said> he went on, sinking his voice and with
his eyes full of undisguised admiration, <said>may I
keep half?</said></p>

<p>She smiled bewitchingly, and in tones low as his
own, replied: <said>Of course you may, but it is utterly
valueless.</said></p>

<p><said>You are quite wrong. Have you ever heard of
the pretty old practice among sailors of splitting
a sixpence with one's sweetheart? This is the
same thing.</said></p>

<p>An indescribable look of triumph leaped into
Adrienne Verne's enigmatical eyes, which for an
instant shone with a brilliancy they did not always
possess. She took the portion of silk he offered
her, and for a moment her fingers lingered in his.</p>

<p>He turned aside quickly, for he had yet another
feat to perform, one that required absolute
command over the nerves and muscles, and he
dared not trust himself to the witchery of Adrienne
Verne.</p>

<p>Harold Calverley, anxious to emulate the highest
attainment of the Indian swordsmen—the slicing
of a lemon while held on another person's hand—
laughingly asked if anyone in the room had
sufficient confidence in his skill to assist him.</p>

<p>There was a pause and a laugh, when somebody
said everyone had the confidence but not the nerve.
Suddenly Adrienne Verne exclaimed:</p>

<p><said>I once saw the feat performed in India, and I
should like to see it again. I'm not the least bit
afraid that you'll fail, Captain Calverley, and I'll
hold the lemon for you.</said></p>

<p><said>You!</said> he rejoined hastily. <said>No, no, I
cannot. I won't run the risk.</said></p>

<p><said>Then it was a boast?</said></p>

<p><said>Not at all,</said> he retorted, stung by her tone.
<said>If you insist——</said></p>

<p><said>I do. There, see, I am quite ready.</said></p>

<p>She held out a hand and arm, both faultless in
outline, and, thus challenged, he could not but
proceed.</p>

<p>Summoning all his nerve and self-control,
Calverley poised the sword, calculated to a nicety
force necessary, and, without a moment's hesita-
tion, brought down the bright, keen blade. The
lemon appeared to fall asunder on the little hand.</p>

<p>Again deafening applause, this time as much for
the holder of the lemon as for the wielder of the
sword.</p>

<p><said>You should not have dared me,</said> he whispered,
half reproachfully. <said>Thank Heaven, it's over!
Your nerve, Adrienne, is amazing—astounding,
but——</said></p>

<p><said>Well, finish your sentence. What does the
<q>but</q> mean?</said></p>

<p><said>Nothing,</said> he answered, lightly.</p>

<p>But it meant a good deal. He could not explain
why the phenomenal nerve of the woman gave him
a momentary feeling of repulsion.</p>

<p>She laughed, and for a brief space they were
separated, she the centre of a crowd who were
offering her their congratulations.</p>

<p>Adrienne Verne was a woman whom one would
call striking rather than beautiful, and yet her
face when animated had an indescribable charm.</p>

<p>Her complexion was of that uniform creamy tint
which comes from a long residence in a hot
climate. There was not a tinge of crimson in it,
even after the excitement of dancing. The colour
seemed to go to her lips, which were firm, full,
and, perhaps, a <choice><corr>touch</corr><orig>thought</orig></choice> too large for the delicate
cast of the rest of her features.</p>

<p>She was fair, so far as her hair was concerned,
but her eyes, her eyebrows and eyelashes were
dark. The hair was very fine in texture, and was
dressed in fluffy masses, which made it look
lighter than it really was. At a distance you would
almost say she was either grey or had powder on
her hair. In certain lights streaks of pale gold
could be clearly seen.</p>

<p>Most people began by being attracted by the hair,
and ended by being fascinated by the eyes. There
was not infrequently a dispute about their colour.
Some said they were dark blue, others that they
were dark grey. Perhaps they varied according to
the light.</p>

<p>But the curious thing about these eyes was that,
as a rule, they were perfectly expressionless. They
suggested mystery, that was all. When she looked
at you, you were conscious she was trying to
penetrate your thoughts, but she never betrayed
her own.</p>

<p>The occasion was one of Adrienne Verne's <soCalled>At
Homes.</soCalled> The scene was her flat near Grosvenor-
square. Always on the look-out for novelty, she
had persuaded Harold Calverley to give a little
entertainment, and he, after much protest about
<soCalled>shewing off,</soCalled> consented.</p>

<p>It is doubtful whether he would have done this
for anyone but Adrienne Verne. The reason is
easily stated—he had fallen in love with her.</p>

<p>It was not in the least surprising. He was
young, impressionable, chivalrous, and had an
honest belief in the inherent goodness of woman.</p>

<p>Maybe, because a good many ill-natured things
were said about Adrienne Verne he was the more
inclined to champion her. Anyhow, he was
continually applying for leave of absence, and
running up to London from Chatham, ostensibly
to see his people, but in reality to see <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Verne,
to dine with her, to take her to theatres and
concerts.</p>

<p>The awkward thing was that nobody who was
anybody knew anything about <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Verne, and
the fact that she was popular with men did not
make her popular with women. Nor, in some odd
way, was it in her favour that she was a widow.</p>

<p>Anyhow, Harold Calverley did not consider it
necessary to tell his martinet of a father, General
Calverley, or his aristocratic mother, an Earl's
daughter, of his acquaintance with the lady.</p>

<p>But some day they would have to know. He
was becoming deeper and deeper in love, and he
had made up his mind to marry her if she would
accept him.</p>

<p><soCalled>At Homes</soCalled> are, as a rule, not very late func-
tions. At ten the guests began to depart. At
half-past only a handful remained. By a quarter
to eleven the last man, save Harold Calverley, was
shaking hands with the charming hostess.</p>

<p>Calverley, at the other end of the room, smoking
a cigarette, was meditating over a leap in the dark.
He was in the mood to propose to Adrienne Verne
and <soCalled>face the music</soCalled> of his outraged parents.</p>

<p>The last man had said his <foreign xml:lang="fr">adieux</foreign>, and Adrienne
was evidently about to come towards him, when
the maid entered with a letter.</p>

<p>Directly she took this letter in her hand he saw
a change go over her face, but it was only for a
moment. She broke open the envelope, read the
letter, and, tearing it into fragments, threw it into
the grate. When she approached him a smile
wreathed her lips.</p>

<p><said>Adrienne,</said> said he, with boyish impulsiveness,
<said>how beautiful you look to-night!</said></p>

<p><said>Don't tell me that,</said> she returned, in a voice
that was almost harsh. <said>Harold, I want to beg of
you a favour—go early, to please me. That sword
business was too much for me. You thought I was
iron-nerved. I wasn't. I felt horribly frightened.</said></p>

<p><said>Do you really want me to go? There's
something I should like to say.</said></p>

<p><said>Another night,</said> she returned, hurriedly.</p>

<p><said>To-morrow? I have two days' leave.</said></p>

<p><said>Yes, to-morrow. Come to tea.</said></p>

<p>He left her a little dashed in spirits. The
evening had begun delightfully, it had ended
dismally.</p>

<p>He walked pensively into Park-lane. The night
was intensely hot. It was fairly early, and there
was no necessity to go direct to the Hotel
Metropole, where he always put up when on his
flying visits to London.</p>

<p>By the time he reached Oxford-street it was
nearly midnight. The last omnibuses were crawl-
ing homewards, the horses plodding languidly
along scarcely responding to the encouraging
<q>click</q> of the drivers.</p>

<p>Suddenly he felt a hand laid on his shoulder.
He turned and saw a man in evening-dress and
Inverness—George Gascoyne, an old college chum
and now a surgeon. Gascoyne had been dining at
his club and was somewhat elated.</p>

<p><said>What, Calverley, old boy! One would think
you were as melancholy as <q>the drone of a
Lincolnshire bagpipe,</q> as old Jack Falstaff has it.
What's gone wrong?</said></p>

<p><said>Nothing. A bit hipped. This infernally
sultry weather, I suppose.</said></p>

<p><said>You want waking up. What do you say to
looking in at a Soho gambling club? The show is
worth a visit—once. Just to stick it in the list of
things one ought to avoid, you know.</said></p>

<p>Calverley was indifferent. All he knew was that
he was not inclined for bed, so the two friends
walked along Oxford-street and turned into Soho-
square.</p>

<p>Gascoyne stopped opposite a quiet-looking house
in grimy Greek-street. The street door opened into
a small, square lobby, feebly lighted; a partition
covered with green baize formed the back of the
lobby, and in the centre of the green baize door
was an oval hole about the size of a man's head.</p>

<p>At a few words from Gascoyne whispered through
this hole, the door was opened by a dark, foreign-
looking man, who entered the names of the visitors
<cb n="2"/>
in a book. They paid a small amount of money,
which constituted them members without any fuss
or ceremony. They heard the sound of a piano as
they ascended the staircase, and were shewn into
a spacious room decorated and furnished quite in
the foreign style—velvet lounges, mirrors, lace
curtains and a good deal of tarnished ornamenta-
tion. The whole aspect was cheap and tawdry.</p>

<p>The company matched its surroundings. The
dresses of the ladies had a decidedly second-hand
look about them; the men might have passed very
well for waiters.</p>

<p>Some of the members were waltzing to a piano
played by a little old grey-headed German, others
were laughing and drinking. The air was thick
with tobacco smoke. Not a few cast a somewhat
suspicious glance at the two young men, who
certainly looked a little out of place in their fault-
less evening attire and their unmistakable air of
good breeding.</p>

<p><said>Where's the gambling you were going to shew
me?</said> whispered Calverley.</p>

<p><said>Oh, that's a floor higher. If this scene of
revelry doesn't take you, we'll try the baccarat
chamber.</said></p>

<p>Calverley was not sorry to quit the hot room,
with its tinsel of gaiety, its almost fetid atmosphere,
and its polyglot sounds—a mixture of the harsh,
the shrill, the nasal and the guttural.</p>

<p>They entered the gaming saloon, where the silence,
by contrast to the pandemonium of the room below,
seemed strange and unnatural. They approached
the long table covered with green cloth unnoticed
by the players who sat round. The latter were far
too absorbed to trouble themselves about anything
save the cards and their chances. Yet the scene in
a way was interesting, if only for the opportunity
it afforded of studying the varied expressions of
the gamesters.</p>

<p><said>I've half a mind to try my luck, Calverley,</said>
whispered Gascoyne.</p>

<p><said>Fools and their money are soon parted,</said> was
the sententious reply of his friend.</p>

<p><said>Never mind; the first seat that's vacant I
shall take.</said></p>

<p>The opportunity soon came. One man who was
either tired or had lost all his money—the latter,
probably, to judge by his white lips and scowling
brow—rose, and Gascoyne dropped into his chair.</p>

<p>At that moment a clap of thunder, one single,
awful crash, shook the house, and for a moment
the startled gamblers looked at each other in
affright.</p>

<p>But card-playing must go on though the heavens
fall. The banker began dealing out the cards
right and left, and the money was being staked
when the door suddenly opened and a swarthy-
complexioned, dark-bearded man, his face twitching
with excitement, rushed straight to the banker and
whispered one word. That word was heard by
everyone in the room.</p>

<p><said>Police!</said></p>

<p>Instantly the men leaped to their feet. One
<foreign xml:lang="fr">croupier</foreign> gathered up the cards, the other tore off
the green cloth, scarcely giving time to the gamblers
to snatch their money.</p>

<p>To Gascoyne and Calverley the matter was very
serious. If the police took them into custody their
names would be published and the scandal would
be extremely unpleasant. Indeed, for a time, it
would be Gascoyne's ruination.</p>

<p><said>Upstairs,</said> whispered Calverley. <said>There's
bound to be a trap-door. It's our only chance.</said></p>

<p>It was a mad idea, but Calverley never stopped
to think. All he wanted was to avoid the police.</p>

<p>They dashed up a couple of flights of narrow
stairs to the top landing. The glimmer of a gas-
jet shewed, as he expected, a trap-door and a
ladder hanging on to a hook against the wall.</p>

<p>In a twinkling, the ladder was planted and the
rusty bolts shot back with some difficulty. They
replaced the trap-door and found themselves in a
loft, its floor thick with dirt and dust. A second
trap had yet to be raised.</p>

<p>At last they were on the roof, and, to go as far
as the corner of the next street was a very easy
matter, for the roof formed two triangles running
lengthwise with a gutter in the centre. Looking
along the channel made by these triangles they
could see that some of the houses had attic windows
opening on the roof.</p>

<p><said>How are we going to get down?</said> exclaimed
Gascoyne. <said>Phew! There's a big drop of rain!
We're in for a shower-bath. Pleasant, upon
my——</said></p>

<p>The words died away in his throat. A cry—
a cry with unmistakable horror in every vibration—
burst upon their astonished ears. It was but one
scream abruptly cut off, as it seemed. It did not
die away naturally.</p>

<p>They listened with beating hearts, but the
sound was not repeated. What was there so
agonising about that cry, so instinct with an appeal
for help, that made both men involuntarily think
of murder? Neither could say.</p>

<p>Some three houses away was an attic window
faintly lit up. Calverley could hardly say by what
impulse he was actuated, but he ran to this
window and looked through. A vivid flash of
lightning made the whole interior visible.</p>

<p><said>Heavens!</said> he cried. <said>Look at that!</said></p>

<p>The next moment he had opened the windows,
which were hung like doors, and was in the room.</p>

<p>A second flash shewed a man lying stretched on
the floor, his face congested, his eyes distended,
his lips swollen.</p>

<p>In an instant Gascoyne was by Calverley's side
and was stooping over the body.</p>

<p><said>By Jove!</said> muttered the surgeon. <said>The man's
dead—strangled!</said></p>

<p>Amid the pattering of the rain was heard a
significant sound in the adjoining room—the sound
of a door closing softly.</p>

<p>The two friends looked at each other. The
same thought was in the minds of both—the
murderer was making his escape. The two rooms
communicated, and quick as thought they rushed in
pursuit. An obstacle awaited them, the door
leading to the landing was locked on the outside!</p>

<p><said>A pretty fix,</said> muttered Gascoyne. <said>Locked
in with a murdered man and no way of explaining
our presence but that we were trying to escape the
consequences of a police raid on a disreputable
gambling club. Nice position for a rising
surgeon!</said></p>

<p>He took his silk handkerchief from his vest and
mopped his forehead. The shock following the
effects of the wine he had drunk had thoroughly
unnerved him. Calverley, on the other hand, was
perfectly cool.</p>

<p><said>Perhaps there is a way out into the passage
from the other room,</said> he suggested.</p>

<p><said>Yes, yes,</said> muttered Gascoyne, <said>I hope to
goodness there is. Hang it, I've dropped my
handkerchief.</said></p>

<p>Leaving his friend groping for his property
Calverley hastened back. His conjecture as to a
second door was right, and he called softly to his
companion.</p>

<p><said>Found your handkerchief?</said> he whispered.</p>

<p><said>Yes, thank goodness. I dared not leave it
behind with my name worked in the corner.</said></p>

<p>They rapidly descended the staircase. The
house was silent and dark. They met no one, they
heard the sound of no one. Within a minute they
were in the pelting rain and racing along the
flooded street.</p>

<milestone unit="tb"/>

<p><q>Please do not come until nine o'clock.—
<name rend="sc">Adrienne</name>.</q></p>

<p>Harold Calverley threw the telegram on the
breakfast-table impatiently. He had to catch the
midnight train to Chatham, and he had looked
forward to a long evening with Adrienne.</p>

<p>He was feverish and uneasy. He could eat nothing.
The exciting events of the previous night were too
fresh in his mind. He opened the newspaper with
a feeling of dread. Yes, there was an account of
the police raid, but not a word about the dead
man. Ought he not to give information to the
police? But Gascoyne, it would injure him in his
profession; besides, he had given his promise not
to say a word.</p>

<p>How the day passed he did not quite know. The
only thing absolutely certain was that he ate little
and had several brandies and sodas. Then he kept
his appointment.</p>

<p>The room into which <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Verne's maid
shewed him was dark save at one end where the
pale moonlight flooded the balcony. He could see
the graceful outline of Adrienne Verne's figure
within the open French windows.</p>

<p>She looked dazzlingly fair in the pale mysterious
light. The profile stood out sharp, clear and
delicate against the sombre background of foliage,
her bosom rose and fell in regular pulsations; the
round shoulders were almost visible beneath the
diaphanous gauze of her summer dress.</p>

<p>She turned her head towards him. A smile
hovered over the coral lips. The long lashes
closed languorously, and then half-opened.</p>

<p><said>Dear, dear Harold,</said> she murmured.</p>

<p>Her words, the soft, enticing whisper, the glance
from beneath those drooping lids, fired him. His
blood coursed through his veins like liquid fire.</p>

<p><said>Tell me, Adrienne,</said> he breathed, carried away
by the impulse of the moment and the vehemence
of his passion, <said>do you love me?</said></p>

<p>She snatched her fingers away, she covered her
face with both hands; her bosom heaved con-
vulsively.</p>

<p>His arm went round her slender waist, and he
drew her to him, trying to remove her hands.</p>

<p><said>Let me see your face,</said> he whispered. <said>I want
to read my fate there.</said></p>

<p>Suddenly she changed her position, removed her
hands, and looked at him. Her face was composed
—more composed than he expected.</p>

<p><said>I am not like other women, remember. I
shall worry you to death.</said></p>

<p><said>Very well, then, I will die.</said></p>

<p>A thrill passed over her; he felt her almost
tremble.</p>

<p><said>Do you promise to love me always—ever—until
death?</said> she persisted.</p>

<p><said>Until death and beyond.</said></p>

<p><said>That does not matter. There is no beyond,</said>
she returned, hastily.</p>

<p>They sat side by side, silent, for some little
<cb n="3"/>
time, resigning themselves to the blissful, absorbing
passion of a newly-found love.</p>

<p>Was Harold Calverley happy? He could scarcely
say. He was infatuated with the witch-like beauty
of the woman, but—well, there is often a good
deal in that fatal but.</p>

<p>Presently she raised her eyes, and those mystical
orbs, now soft and languorous, travelled over the
young man's face.</p>

<p><said>You have made me so happy, dearest Harold.
Tell me now, when did you first love me?</said></p>

<p><said>How can I answer such a question, Adrienne,</said>
said he, in a tone of forced gaiety. <said>I do not
know. I suppose I gradually grew to love you.</said></p>

<p><said>By degrees? Ah, that is not my way. With
me I either love at once—or hate. I think directly
I saw you I loved you. I could not help it. Kiss
me, Harold. I want to know that you are there,
that it is not a dream.</said></p>

<p>She spoke with a feverish intensity, every
accent vibrating with passion. He kissed her. Her
lips seemed to fasten upon his as though she
wished to transfuse her nature with his.</p>

<p><said>You do love me, darling, do you not?</said></p>

<p><said>Yes, of course.</said></p>

<p><said>Of course,</said> she echoed. <said>And are you happy
—as I am?</said></p>

<p><said>I hope so.</said></p>

<p><said>You hope so. How coldly you speak! I want
you to be sure. I want you to feel that I love you
with the only love that is worth anything—the love
that makes a woman dare anything, do anything,
stoop to anything to gain the heart she longs for.
That is my love for you, Harold; cannot you
understand?</said></p>

<p>Her voice sank almost to a murmur. He could
feel her thrill with emotion. The lips, usually so
crimson, were pallid, and, parting tremulously,
shewed her small, white, even, strong teeth.</p>

<p>Harold Calverley left the house in a delirium of
the senses which he did not attempt to analyse,
nor could he had he so wished. Yet his intoxica-
tion of bliss was dashed with shadows, not merely
the misgivings as to what the General and his
mother would say, but something darker, something
absolutely indefinable.</p>

<p>To add to his uneasiness he missed his train.
There was no possibility of reaching Chatham
before the morning.</p>

<p>While standing irresolutely it occurred to him
that Gascoyne's place was near Victoria. He
would get a shakedown there.</p>

<p>Gascoyne, looking pale and wretched, received
him in a flurried manner.</p>

<p><said>It is as I suspected,</said> said he, with some agita-
tion. <said>That man was murdered—after the fashion of
Thuggism. A handkerchief slipped round the neck
and the thumbs ground into the windpipe, one
each side. It was all over in half a minute.
There's the evening paper—you can read all about
it for yourself.</said></p>

<p>The dead man was named Philip Trafford. He
had lodged in the house for some weeks, but no
one knew anything about him. But this was not
singular, for all the rest of the premises were let
out for business purposes. Undoubtedly he had
been strangled, but at present the whole affair was
wrapped in mystery.</p>

<p><said>Unpleasant business, isn't it? If I only had
the pluck to speak, I fancy I could give the police
the clue,</said> went on Gascoyne. <said>Look here. You
remember my dropping my silk handkerchief and
groping for it in the dark. I picked up this as
well. I didn't find it out until I got home.</said></p>

<p><said><emph>That!</emph></said> almost shrieked Calverley.</p>

<p>He turned ghastly white, and his eyes had in
them an expression of unspeakable horror.</p>

<p>It was the half of the silken scarf he had
severed! The other half he had at that moment
in his pocket as a <foreign xml:lang="fr">gage d'amour</foreign>.</p>

<p><said>My dear fellow,</said> exclaimed Gascoyne alarmed,
<said>what ails you?</said></p>

<p><said>I'm going to take this scarf,</said> he rejoined,
fiercely. <said>Give it to me, I say.</said></p>

<p>He snatched the silken piece of gauze from the
astonished surgeon's hand and thrust it into his
pocket.</p>

<p><said>You can come with me, if you like,</said> he went
on, with a reckless laugh, <said>just to see I'm not
going to give you away to the police.</said></p>

<p><said>Wait outside,</said> Calverley whispered hoarsely a
little later. Their cab was at the door of the
flats where <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Verne lived. <said>I shan't be long.</said></p>

<p>Nor was he. Gascoyne saw him come out of the
doorway in a quarter of an hour's time staggering
like a drunken man. The surgeon had to assist
him into the cab.</p>

<p><said>Would you like to know the solution of the
mystery in Greek-street?</said> he broke out, boister-
ously. <said>I have just left the woman who strangled
the man we found. He was her husband, and,
Heaven help me! I thought I loved her, and only
two hours ago asked her to marry me.</said></p>

<p>He sank back in the corner of the cab and buried
his face in his hands. He could say no more.</p>

<p>But afterwards, bit by bit, the story came out.
Adrienne Verne undoubtedly was an adventuress,
but, perhaps—who can say?—not wholly bad.
She had had a successful career as a Circe of the
Atlantic—one of those fascinating women who find
the great ocean greyhounds very profitable areas
for their ingenuity whether in the way of robbery
or blandishments.</p>

<p>In an evil hour she married—married a man who
was thoroughly vicious and who had done time.
She betrayed him over some swindling transaction,
he was sentenced to five years penal servitude, and
he swore when he came out of prison he would
pursue her to the ends of the earth and have his
revenge.</p>

<p>That note, delivered to Adrienne Verne late the
previous evening, which contracted her face with a
sudden spasm, told her that his vengeance was
near.</p>

<p>She was a bold and determined woman, and she
did not hesitate. She hated and feared this man,
<choice><corr>Philip</corr><orig>Phillip</orig></choice> Trafford, and she loved with all the force
of her nature Harold Calverley. She went to the
house in Greek-street. There was a stormy inter-
view, but she, taking the man unawares, strangled
him as skilfully as any Thug. And she used the
half of the silken scarf to do it.</p>

<p>The next day <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Verne's furnished flat was
empty. The sudden death of a relative, she told
the agent, had called her away. Not a word did
Calverley or Gascoyne ever divulge, and the mystery
of Greek-street, so far as the police and the public
are concerned, remains a mystery to this day.</p>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>
