<TEI x-xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title>With Her Own Hands</title>
      <author>Charles E. Pearce</author>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Transcribed by</resp>
        <name>Paul Flo Williams</name>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>The Charles Pearce Society</publisher>
      <availability>
        <p>Charles Pearce died in 1924, making his works out of copyright in the UK as of 1995.</p>
      </availability>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>First published on Saturday 26 July 1902, in the Lancashire Daily Post (archived by BNA as the "Lancashire Evening Post").</bibl>
<p>Author of "Besieged in Lucknod," "John Dale,
Convict," "Miss Doon, of Manchester,"
"In the Coils of Klondike," &amp;c.</p>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en-GB">
<body>
<head type="main">With Her Own Hands</head>

<p><said>Is it for the last time, Janet?</said></p>
<p><said>You know best about that.</said></p>
<p>The fire which had for a moment flashed in Stephen
Musgrave's dark eyes died down, leaving them sullen
and expressionless. Though his glance was fixed on
the fair landscape he saw nothing. The grassy slope
descending to the placid stream, the line of pollards,
the path on the other side of the river leading to the
Hodsbourne Woods, black against the dull red of the
setting sun, were to him invisible. The picture before
his eyes was the proud, disdainful face of Janet Lang-
don.</p>
<p>The girl stood erect, every muscle, every nerve of
her handsome, vigorous body stiffened into rebellion.
When Stephen put his question, she turned from him
abruptly, her blue eyes merciless, scorn in every line
of her beautiful face. He heard defiance in her
answer, in her voice, but he could not see how that
defiance was belied by the quiver of the red lips.</p>
<p><said>You'd better marry George Hurst and have done
with it,</said> said he, with bitter emphasis.</p>
<p><said>Keep your advice for those who want it, Stephen
Musgrave.</said></p>
<p><said>Why don't you say you are tired of me? I should
know what you meant then,</said> he cried, passionately.</p>
<p><said>Really? Not you. You're too stupid.</said></p>
<p>Her contempt made him wince, the smouldering
fire leaped once more to his eyes, his mouth was com-
pressed until it became little more than a white line.</p>
<p>He lost self control and seized the girl's wrist
roughly—more roughly than he imagined.</p>
<p><said>Listen, Janet,</said> said he, sinking his voice until
it was scarcely more than a hoarse whisper. <said>You're
the first girl who's ever trifled with me, and, by
Heaven! you shall be the last. I will never let you
go, mind that. Marry Hurst, by all means—I pity
him, poor beggar.</said></p>
<p>He flung her arm from him as one jerks away some-
thing of no moment, and laughed exultantly.</p>
<p>She turned as fierce as he, her eyes ablaze, her
cheeks scarlet with passion.</p>
<p><said>I hate you—you—you coward!</said> she cried.</p>
<p>He had roused her from her contemptuous mood,
and he drank in her enhanced beauty with a savage
pleasure.</p>
<p><said>Coward, is it? Not a coward, Janet, where a
woman is concerned.</said></p>
<p>Quick as lightning his arm was round her waist,
and he kissed her full on the lips.</p>
<p><said>Take that to George Hurst.</said></p>
<p>The sharp sound of the girl's hand on his cheek
startled the still air like the crack of a whip.</p>
<p><said>And that is my parting gift,</said> she cried. Break-
ing from him, she ran, her bosom heaving, her lips
tremulous, along the path across the meadow where
beyond the common Hodsbourne village lay nestled
in the hollow.</p>
<p>Stephen Musgrave watched the girl's shapely figure
till, passing through the gate at the end of the path,
she was lost to view; then, with his eyes fixed on the
ground and his hands in his pocket, descended the
slope towards the river. He still felt the sting of her
hand, but his smarting cheek, instead of exasperating
him, sent his love to fever heat.</p>
<p>The glow of the water cooled into gray, the
shadow of the pollards became black as ink, the sky
was overspread with the opalescence of a midsummer
night; Stephen Musgrave, his head bent, wandered
slowly along the river bank.</p>
<p>The man was nursing his love, to what end he
knew not, though certain vague thoughts were be-
ginning to take shape in his mind. Janet Langdon,
a tempest of emotions raging within her, was hasten-
ing homewards, carrying her head high with a sense
of victory. If she had anything clear in her whirling
brain, it was a desire to inflict condign punishment
and vexation on Stephen Musgrave, even if she made
it up afterwards. The fiercer the quarrel and the
more relentless the punishment, the sweeter the re-
conciliation.</p>
<p>By the time Janet reached her mother's house the
white heat of passion had cooled. She pushed open
the garden gate, and a sharp pain brought back an
irritating remembrance of Stephen Musgrave. She
looked at her wrist; gray though the light was, five
red marks showed distinctly on her white flesh.</p>
<p>She felt the sting of humiliation, Musgrave's con-
temptuous gesture, the kiss that had blistered her lips,
the taunt about George Hurst—it all returned and
sent her quivering from head to foot.</p>
<p>She was tempted to stay out until calmness re-
turned. Her mother's pestering questions just then
would be beyond endurance. But it was too late, the
creaking of the rusty hinges had been heard. <abbr>Mrs.</abbr>
Langdon met her half-way down the garden path.</p>
<p><said>Come in, Janet, come in. I was afraid you'd be
late. Farmer Hurst's inside.</said></p>
<p><said>I don't want to see him to-night,</said> answered the
gal, sullenly.</p>
<p><said>Don't be a fool, child. He's been waiting here
an hour, fidgeting and looking at his watch every five
minutes. D' you think I can't tell what that means?
He wanted to know where you'd gone—said he'd
walk and meet you, but I wasn't going to let him
slip. I dropped a word that you'd gone along by the
river, past Patcham's corner, and that was enough.
I saw his jaw drop.</said></p>
<p>Patcham's Corner was on Musgrave's land, and
<abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Langdon's diplomacy effected its object. Hurst
said he would wait until Janet came back.</p>
<p>At her mother's words the girl's bosom rose and
fell. Her riotous nerves tingled. A glorious triumph
was within her grasp—a triumph over Stephen Mus-
grave. George Hurst had been a widower six years,
and the prophecy of the village gossips that he would
take to himself a second wife within a <choice><corr>twelvemonth</corr><orig>twlevemonth</orig></choice>
after the death of his first wife had been falsified. As
he had prospered exceedingly and still remained
single, the only reasonable explanation was that there
was no one in Hodsbourne good enough for him.</p>
<p>Janet knew all this, but she had never troubled
about the rich farmer until handsome Stephen Mus-
grave came after her. It was flattering when Stephen
openly showed his attention, but she was not going
to be added to the list of his conquests.</p>
<p>There was no one she could so well play off against
Stephen Musgrave as the unattainable Farmer Hurst,
and she had succeeded in bringing Stephen to his
knees much more effectually than she anticipated, or,
may be, intended.</p>
<p>In the arena of flirtation she had defeated the
champion. Stephen Musgrave, hitherto unconquered,
had gone down before her, and so far victory was
sweet. But had she herself issued from the conflict
unwounded? And was she prepared to deliver the
<q>coup de grace</q> to Stephen Musgrave by marrying
George Hurst?</p>
<p>She had never bargained for that fierce quarrel,
and now the strain was over her feminine armour was
gone, her weapons dropped. George Hurst had come
at a moment when she was utterly defenceless.</p>
<p>Dazed and confused, she followed <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Langdon
round the house to the kitchen entrance.</p>
<p><said>Mercy on me, you're not fit to be seen! You
look as if you had stuck your head in a furze bush.</said></p>
<p>The girl had flung her hat on the table. The
masses of her tawny hair were clustered loosely about
her forehead, the coil, usually so neat and shining,
was undone.</p>
<p>Her mother considered her ruffled hair slatternly,
most men would have thought it gave a piquancy to
her scarlet cheeks, her liquid blue eyes, her red lips,
her dimpled chin.</p>
<p><said>Gracious! You are not going to see <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Hurst
like that? Whatever will he think?</said></p>
<p><said>I don't care what he thinks,</said> returned Janet,
doggedly.</p>
<p>She had caught sight of her reflection in the
mirror, the tumult of emotions had intensified her
brilliant colouring, the fire in her eyes roused by
Stephen Musgrave's kiss had not died away. She
felt instinctively her beauty was provoking. Some
demon within her urged her to see if the staid, the
ultra-respectable, middle aged man could be tempted
out of his coldness. Her mother would have detained
her, but she evaded maternal solicitude and dis-
appeared.</p>
<p><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Langdon sank into a Windsor chair, her large
features working convulsively, and it was as much as
she could do to avoid throwing her apron over her
head and weeping.</p>
<p><said>Farmer Hurst marry a slattern, and him used to
everything so spick and span, first in his wife's time,
and next in his sister's? Never! But there, I
always said Janet would stand in her own light.</said></p>
<p>She could not control her anxiety. She rose, stole
into the passage, and listened at the door of the next
room. She could hear Hurst's deep growl, but his
words were indistinguishable.</p>
<p><said>Seems to have all the talk to himself,</said> she mur-
mured. <said>I wonder whether that's a good or bad
sign,</said> and crept back to the kitchen.</p>
<p>Presently she heard the door open, a heavy step
traversed the passage, the rustle of a skirt followed.
<cb/>
The outer door closed abruptly; there was no lovers'
lingering farewell.</p>
<p><said>Nothing's come of it,</said> lamented <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Langdon.
<said>The girl's thrown away her chance. I knew she
would.</said></p>
<p>Before the woman could rise from her chair Janet
came hastily into the room, the scarlet of her cheeks
and lips vanished, the light gone from her eyes. Her
disordered hair, which a quarter an hour ago had
given life to the picture, now brought to it the aspect
of death.</p>
<p><said>No wonder you look like a ghost,</said> snapped her
mother. <said>I suppose now you're sorry you didn't do
what I told you—make yourself tidy and respectable?</said></p>
<p><said>Yes, I am. Perhaps if I had he wouldn't have
wanted to marry me.</said></p>
<p><said>Eh? Then he did ask you?</said> returned <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Lang-
don, breathlessly. <said>Of course, you said yes?</said></p>
<p>The girl nodded, and stood motionless, her eyes
fixed on the ground, her left hand grasping her right
wrist where Stephen Musgrave had left the marks of
his fingers.</p>
<p>A sob, a passionate cry, and the next moment her
mother was left alone in the midst of pious thanks-
givings.</p>
<milestone unit="tb"/>
<p>Farmer Hurst evidently intended to make up for
tardiness in taking a second wife by the celerity of
his preparations for the wedding.</p>
<p>Perhaps he thought Janet might alter her mind,
for the banns were at once put up; he packed off
her sister to a cottage about a mile from the Rectory
Farm, a good deal of his old furniture was replaced
by modern articles, more in accordance with the taste
of a young bride, and the wedding was celebrated
with congratulations and not a little adverse criticism.</p>
<p>Still, outwardly all seemed to indicate fair weather.
When Farmer Hurst led his bride from the vestry to
the porch his square, hard face wore the slightly
cunning, wholly self-satisfied smile familiar to his
associates on market days when he had succeeded in
driving a close bargain, but the general opinion was
that Janet did not look as a bride should, radiant with
happiness.</p>
<p>Only once did her expression change, and that was
when the crowd pressed forward and packed the
porch. Despite the gloom, her eyes caught sight of
Stephen Musgrave—his brown face no longer of its
healthy ruddiness, his lips white, his eyes sunken.</p>
<p>Farmer Hurst saw him, too, and the cunning smile
curved his mouth a little more.</p>
<p><said>Won't you alter your mind, Stephen, and come
up to the farm? There'll be rare doings to-day, I'll
warrant,</said> said he, condescendingly.</p>
<p><said>Thank 'ee. I'll choose my own time for
coming,</said> returned Musgrave, his sullen glance fixed
on Janet.</p>
<p>The newly-made husband straightened himself, as
much as to say, <q>I've fought fair and won the day,
and now I can afford to be generous.</q></p>
<p>The nine days' wonder became a commonplace fact,
and Janet Langdon, the village coquette, was for-
gotten in <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Hurst, the farmer's wife. Stephen
Musgrave dropped out of sight, allowing his man,
Ralph Herne, the use of his cottage at Patcham's
Corner, and himself living in London.</p>
<p>Autumn mists, winter frost and snow, were gone,
and with the spring farming woke into activity.
George Hurst, busy all day among his men, out of
whom it was said he got every ounce of work, came
home mud-bespattered, smelling of the soil and the
rankness of greasy wool. Sheep-shearing had that
day commenced.</p>
<p>The farmer threw himself into the solid armchair
by the side of the great fireplace. He was a big,
ungainly man, and his bulky form, his sprawling,
gaitered legs, loomed large in the fitful glow of the
burning wood.</p>
<p>The table was spread for the last meal of the day,
a compromise between supper and tea, and a buxom
farming wench was moving heavily about the brick-
paved kitchen.</p>
<p>Hurst sat silently for two or three minutes staring
straight before him, then his coarse fingers clenched
with the suddenness of a nervous spasm, and, without
shifting his eyes, he said harshly:</p>
<p><said>Where is your mistress, Molly?</said></p>
<p>Before the girl could answer the door opened and
his wife entered. She must have heard his question,
but she said nothing. She took her accustomed seat
at the bottom of the table, and scarcely glanced at
her husband.</p>
<p>In the glare of the lamp which the girl lighted
after Janet was seated George Hurst looked even less
sightly than before. The light revealed his hard,
square, seamed face, the scanty grayish hair, damp
with perspiration and plastered on his narrow fore-
head, a furrow round the head left by his felt hat
showing distinctly. It brought into prominence his
heavy, prominent jaw, his large ears, his loose, ill-
fitting clothes.</p>
<p>He pulled his chair to the table with unnecessary
noise and helped himself to the beef and beer, eating
with the voracity of an animal. Not a word did he
say to his wife, though every now and then a furtive
half-savage glance darted upwards from beneath his
shaggy brows.</p>
<p>Nearly a year had made a great difference in Janet,
but whether she had improved or deteriorated it was
difficult to say. The figure was fully developed, and
in harmony of line was perfect. The beauty of the
face had ripened, but it had not the suggestion of
sweetness, the old lurking smile in the dimples. Faint
lines slightly depressing the corners of the firm lips
were just visible.</p>
<p>She was sitting almost as motionless as a statue,
her proud, scornful face turned from her husband,
when a clatter of crockery aroused her. Hurst had
thrust his plate from him with a jerk, and, planting
his elbows square on the table, was glaring at her
with a spot of angry colour in each cheek. The beer
jug by his side was empty, and had been more than
once replenished.</p>
<p><said><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Hurst,</said> said he, with a thump of the fist
that made the plates and dishes dance. <said>Listen to
me. You're not stone deaf, though you look it.
I've got something to tell you.</said></p>
<p>The young woman made no reply, her scorn only
deepened.</p>
<p><said>A fortnight ago, when I caught Ralph Herne, the
servant of your old flame, Steve Musgrave, near the
big barn, I swore if I found him foxing round again,
I'd mark him. I've kept my word. The hound'll
reach home with some stripes on his face he hadn't got
when he set out to deliver a love message to another
man's wife.</said></p>
<p>He paused to watch the effect of his words. If pos-
sible, his wife sat more statuesque than before. The
red spots on the farmer's cheeks deepened.</p>
<p><said>See here, <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Hurst,</said> he roared, <said>I'll make you
speak. I'll tame you yet. Ralph Herne'll take back
something else besides his marks. <said>Tell your master,</said>
says I, <said>my whip cuts deep.</said></said></p>
<p>If he thought to rouse her, he was mistaken. Not a
muscle in her cold, impassive face quivered. She rose
from the table and rang the bell.</p>
<p><said>Molly,</said> said she, <said>your master has finished.</said></p>
<p>The inflection of her voice showed the double mean-
ing, but whether Hurst's sluggish brain grasped the
allusion to his own words is doubtful.</p>
<p>The entry of the servant silenced him. He sat with
his elbows resting on the table, his chin buried in his
big brown hands, his face flushed to a deep purple, his
eyes swollen, his veins in his temples <choice><corr>throbbing</corr><orig>trobbing</orig></choice>, dead
to everything but his own jealousy.</p>
<p>Rumour had <choice><corr>been</corr><orig>ben</orig></choice> busy with Farmer Hurst's
domestic affairs since his marriage. The most discreet
of couples cannot conceal their differences from their
servants. It was an open secret that during a fierce
quarrel Hurst had struck his wife, and she swore she
would never speak to him again. Two months had
gone since that terrible scene, and Janet had kept her
word.</p>
<p>In marrying George Hurst she thought to show
Stephen Musgrave her independence, but in reality
she had thrown away freedom for slavery. George
Hurst had no notion of giving something for nothing
and as he was rich and worshipped riches, he considered
he had performed an act of condescension in marrying
Janet Langdon, who had nothing, and that she was
deficient in gratitude when she was indifferent to him
and his affairs.</p>
<p>In truth, she was as unsuitable for the Rectory Farm
and its master as were the modern furniture, the piano,
the mirrors for what was called the best room, with its
dark oak panelling and great beam running across the
low ceiling.</p>
<p>It was not her indifference, her listlessness, her
thorough unfitness to be the farmer's wife which
rankled. Though all this formed the groundwork of
Hurst's ill-humour, it did not do more than vex and
mortify him. But when it came to his ears that Ralph
Herne, Stephen Musgrave's man, was continually
hanging about the Rectory Farm, jealousy took the
place of ill-temper, and jealousy <choice><corr>soon</corr><orig>son</orig></choice> grew into hatred.</p>
<p>The day following the encounter with Ralph Herne
the farmer was due at Ralston Market. He had
drank heavily after the scene with his wife and awoke
with parched throat, yellow skin, and shaking hands.
Morose and taciturn, he breakfasted by himself, and
set out at an early hour on his roan.</p>
<p>Night came, he did not return, and Janet,
assuming he had got tipsy at the farmers' dinner,
and had stopped at Ralston, was not surprised.
But when the next night arrived and he was still
absent, it was time to make inquiries. She sent a
messenger to Ralston, and the man came back with
the news that Farmer Hurst had left the town about
six on the evening of the market day. This was
strange and alarming, and still more alarming was
the intelligence which reached the Rectory Farm in
the early morning that the man had been found float-
ing in the river—dead.</p>
<milestone unit="tb"/>
<p>There was little doubt as to the cause of the farmer's
disappearance. The nearest road to Ralston was by
crossing the river, not by the bridge, but by the ford
a mile lower down. As a rule, the water at the ford
was no more than a couple of feet deep, but April
and May were rainy months, and the river was swollen.
The roan had evidently stumbled, for its knees were
cut, and unable to recover its footing had been swept
away by the current, and so drowned together with
its master.</p>
<p>This was the theory, and a very feasible one every-
body considered it to be. The only question was,
what had become of the farmer? The river was
dragged for a couple of miles below the ford, but
the body was not found. To pursue the search beyond
this point was considered useless, for the river here
widened into an estuary, where the mud was of con-
siderable depth; besides, why should not the body
have been washed into the sea? Maybe at low water
some day the corpse would be discovered, but for
the present the mystery must remain unsolved.</p>
<p>Hodsbourne was not a little scandalised when Janet
Hurst refused to put on mourning, but she did not
want supporters who declared that she was right. In
the first place, said they, her husband had treated
her badly, and in the second, he had not left her a
penny piece. Molly and Giles Hoskins, the herdsman,
told how they had been called into the room by the
master to witness his signature, and they wrote their
names in proper form on the document.</p>
<p>The will by which the whole of the property was
left to the farmer's sister was perfectly valid, and
the odd thing was that it was made the night before
Hurst set out on his ill-fated journey. That he must
have had some presentiment of his approaching end
was the solemn belief of the village.</p>
<p>Three weeks went over; again Stephen Musgrave
and Janet Hurst were walking in the meadow sloping
to the river. They had been talking in low, earnest
tones, and then had come a silence.</p>
<p><said>Best let bygones be bygones,</said> said she at last,
slowly, and with an evident effort. <said>I've had enough
of married life.</said></p>
<p><said>Yes, with a man you hated. I know all about it,
Janet. You married Hurst to spite me, but now my
turn's come. Haven't I waited patiently? If I
haven't kept the oath you made me take the night we
met in Hodsbourne Woods, it was because no mortal
man could. Have I forgotten your confession?</said></p>
<p>Janet's face paled a little, a look half of fright, half
of shame came into her eyes.</p>
<p>Her confession! Well, not so much a confession as
an admission, extorted from her by Stephen one even-
ing when they met by accident—an accident, at least,
on Janet's part—in Hodsbourne Woods.</p>
<p>It was that fatal day when her husband struck her.
All her being was in revolt; her thoughts rushed back
to Stephen Musgrave, and when Stephen met her he
spoke not in the old vainglorious spirit, but
sympathisingly, respectfully, almost humbly. He,
too, like herself, had changed, and the strange softness
of his voice, the unwonted tenderness in his eyes,
broke down her self-control, and she sobbed out the
truth in his arms. She felt he was more generous than
she had a right to expect, and this increased her
penitence. She owned she loved him when she
married George Hurst; that she loved him still.</p>
<p>Then a flood of shame and remorse swept over her,
she made him swear that he would never seek to see
her again, and he reluctantly consented, but failed to
keep his promise.</p>
<p>After his reminder of her confession, Stephen
pursued his advantage. She could not, he urged, deny
that she loved him. She was now free, what was there
to prevent their marriage?</p>
<p><said>I—I don't know. Oh, Steve,</said> she burst out,
<said>swear to me that——</said></p>
<p>She stopped, she pressed her hand to her bosom, a
thrill—nay, a shudder—seemed to go over her, and
the hand Stephen was clasping became as cold as ice.</p>
<p><said>I am a fool,</said> she exclaimed, with a half-hysterical
laugh.</p>
<p>The man heard her silently, his head bent low down,
his grasp over her cold fingers gradually tightening.
Suddenly she withdrew her hand, and, flinging her
arms round his neck, pressed her lips to his as though
to make amends for some unjust thoughts concerning
him.</p>
<p>Stephen suggested being married in London, and he
hastened to town, made all arrangements, took apart-
ments for Janet and her mother, to whom she had
returned on the contents of her husband's will being
known, and came back to Hodsbourne. For Janet's
sake, he urged the utmost secrecy. The villagers
might make an unpleasant demonstration if it got wind
she intended to marry again, especially as there was
no absolute evidence Farmer Hurst was dead; and
so Stephen never went near <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Langdon's house,
but met Janet at the old spot by the river.</p>
<p>The meeting of this cold, dreary wet May afternoon, so
unlike the May of the poets, was to be their last in
Hodsbourne. It was settled that Janet and her mother
should leave by an early train the following morning,
and Stephen was to precede them that night.</p>
<p>Stephen Musgrave was, he said, establishing a busi-
ness in London, and he never wanted to see Hods-
bourne again. Janet was equally anxious to leave the
place where she had passed her miserable married life.</p>
<p>They wandered on, Stephen talking continuously,
even feverishly, of his plans for the future and Janet
listening in silence. Neither of them noticed how
far they had gone. It was only by Janet shivering
violently that Stephen awakened to the fact that
they were two miles from Hodsbourne, and that the
drizzle had become an absolute downpour.</p>
<p><said>You will catch your death of cold. What shall
we do?</said> he cried, anxiously.</p>
<p>What he could do was obvious. His own house
which he had let to Ralph Herne was but a hundred
yards away—why not take shelter there? But this
did not seem to occur to him, and when Janet sug-
gested it he made an objection on the score that
the place was not fit for her to enter, the Hernes
were such dirty people. But she persisted, and at
last he consented, though with evident reluctance.</p>
<p>Desolate enough Musgrave's house looked in its
misty shroud. The garden was choked with rank
vegetation, the leaves of the previous autumn had
not been cleared away, the paths were run over
with weeds. A close, unwholesome, damp smell
seemed to pour from the interior when the door
was opened by <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Herne, a dark-browed woman
of diminutive stature, who started with surprise,
almost with alarm, as it seemed, when she recognised
her visitor.</p>
<p>Stephen bade the woman light a fire in the best
room and make some tea, and without a word of
welcome to Janet, which would have been
only natural, for it was her first visit to the
house, sank into a wicker chair, staring blankly at
the damp wood spluttering and hissing. His silence
was in strange contrast to his talkativeness of a
quarter of an hour ago.</p>
<p>The acrid smoke filled the room, and set Janet
coughing, and the heavy rain having ceased, she
wandered into the garden at the rear of the house.
Here the desolation was even more pronounced than
in the front. The neglect extended to the garden
implements. Close to a shattered sundial was a
spade flung down when it was last used, and left,
its blade to rust, its handle to rot.</p>
<p>As her eye travelled from the lop-sided dial to
the spade she noted that at one spot close to both
there had been an effort at cultivation. It was a
bed of mustard and cress, just ready for eating. The
tender, level green was fresh and inviting, and she
cut a quantity with a little pearl-handled penknife.</p>
<p>Something of the first meal with the man she loved
should be prepared with her own hands, and, to
complete the salad, she looked about for lettuces, but
found none.</p>
<p>She went into the house, washed the mustard and
cress, arranged it daintily on a plate, and took it
into the room where she had left Stephen. She met
<abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Herne in the passage, and noticed how the
woman started back with scared face, and brushed
past her.</p>
<p>Stephen Musgrave was in the same brooding atti-
tude. With a loving caress she bade him come to
the table, which was laid for tea. She had to tell
him twice before he heard her, and when he rose,
she saw his face was white and drawn, his eyes wild
and staring.</p>
<p><said>Stephen!</said></p>
<p>Her voice died away in her throat, frozen with
horror. The man was swaying backwards and
forwards, his trembling right hand straight out
before him. A rattling noise came from his throat,
he seemed to be struggling with some words his
pallid lips refused to utter. Then she saw he was
pointing to the dish of mustard and cress on which
his frenzied eyes were fixed.</p>
<p><said>Good Heavens!</said> he screamed. <said>That——</said></p>
<p>And reeling past the frightened girl he dashed out
of the room. For a minute she stood paralysed with
a strange fear, a sinister foreboding. Then she ran
to the door—it was locked. She rattled the handle
and hammered the panels with her clenched hands.
No one came, yet she could hear rapid footsteps.
After that all was still.</p>
<p>Twenty-four hours later, a man was found wander-
ing some 30 miles from Hodsbourne, and taken into
custody as one not fitted to be at large. He was
without a hat, his dress was torn and muddy, his hair
dishevelled, his face convulsed with a nameless fear,
in his eyes the glare of madness. This man was
Stephen Musgrave.</p>
<p>For some days no light could be thrown on the
mystery. Then it was noticed Herne and his wife had
disappeared from Musgrave's house, and this set
people thinking.</p>
<p>The garden was dug over, and beneath the bed of
mustard and cress was found the body of Farmer
Hurst.</p>
<p>The hue and cry was raised, and the Hernes cap-
tured in a distant part of the country. The woman
doggedly held her tongue, but the man, to save his
neck, confessed how Stephen Musgrave had schemed
to murder Hurst.</p>
<p>A couple of stable buckets tied together, with a yard
or so of loose rope between them, placed in the ford,
sufficed to throw the horse, a blow from a bludgeon as
Hurst lay floundering stunned the rider, and drowning
completed the hideous work. Then the body was
brought to Herne's garden and mustard and cress seed
sown over the grave, to cover the freshly-turned soil
as rapidly as possible and avert suspicion in case any-
body came prying about.</p>
<p>Herne's confession did not save him. He was
hanged, and his wife sentenced to twenty years' penal
servitude. No suspicion rested on Janet. She had
never been seen with Stephen Musgrave, and Herne
was mercifully silent about her visit to the house from
which she had escaped by the window after Ralph and his
wife, fearing discovery was impending, locked her in
to gain a start for their flight.</p>
<p>A prematurely aged woman, with the light gone
from her eyes, her once tawny hair of a rusty white,
she will bear her secret with her to the grave.</p>
<p>Stephen Musgrave, <soCalled>detained</soCalled> at Broadmoor
Criminal Lunatic Asylum, never recovered his sanity.
All day long, and sometimes far into the night, his
hands perpetually went through the action of sowing
seeds: every now and then his eyes glanced furtively,
and those nearest heard him mutter: <said>It will grow
quickly—quickly. They will never find out, and then
we will be married.</said></p>
<p>One day the attendant, taking Musgrave along one
of the upper corridors, had his attention diverted for a
moment. Something leaped past him into the air and
dropped over the stair rail forty feet on to the stone
pavement below.</p>
<p>Stephen Musgrave's mad brain would be tortured by
conscience no more.</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>


































